War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history of the greatest of
all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price of empire.
In a world made unstable by issues of
the First World War unresolved by the
peace treaty which ended that struggle,
dictators rose and their ambitions
brought Europe once more to the brink of
conflict.
In the second episode of The Price of
Empire, Europe crashed over the brink
when an unlikely alliance between
Germany and the Soviet Union made each
bold enough to move on Poland.
It is now the early spring of 1940. Six
months have passed with little action,
the phony war.
That is about to end and a new word is
to be added to the vocabulary of
warfare,
Blitzkrieg.
On January the 10th, 1940, a German
military aircraft made a forced landing
at Mechelen-sur-Meuse in Belgium.
A board was Major Helmut Reinberger, a
staff officer of the 7th Airborne
Division.
In his possession was a complete copy of
Fall Gelb, Case or Plan Yellow, the
German plan for the invasion of Western
Europe.
The loss of this document to the enemy
was, according to the German Chief of
Operations, catastrophic. Hitler was
forced to postpone his invasion until
the spring, much to the relief of his
high command, which had been arguing for
a halt to allow for repair, rest, and
re-equipment.
That delay was the phony war.
Plan Yellow being compromised now
presented General Erich von Manstein
with the opportunity to press again his
invasion strategy, which had earlier
been rejected.
Plan Yellow was little more than a
re-hashing of the offensive plan with
which Germany had gone to war in 1914.
Essentially, an attack across the
Belgian border outflanking France's
defensive preparations. It was the
strategy that the allies expected.
The dreadful losses of the First World
War, 4 and 1/2 million French
casualties, almost 1 and 1/2 million
dead, had persuaded France that the
future of war lay with the entrenched
soldier and the machine gun.
Between the wars, France had spent vast
amounts of money on preparing a
defensive posture.
Most of the money, perhaps 3 billion
French francs, had gone on a fortified
installation named for the Minister of
War who had initiated it.
Andre Maginot
The Maginot Line fortified the border
between France and Germany.
It was equipped with an underground
railway, underground cinemas, and a
garrison of half a million soldiers
ready to repel any direct German
assault.
This supposedly impregnable position
would, or so it was argued, oblige
Germany to attack through Belgium along
the lines of the 1914 offensive.
And so it was here, from late 1939, that
the French and British concentrated
their forces.
Had Plan Yellow, the attack across the
Belgian border, been implemented, the
outcome is unknowable.
It would surely have been a tighter
struggle than the demolition job that
lay ahead.
With Plan Yellow shelved following the
plane crash in Mechelen-sur-Meuse,
the German High Command was forced to
consider an alternative strategy.
This was the moment for Erich von
Manstein, a professional soldier in the
Prussian tradition.
By mid-February, Hitler had accepted von
Manstein's plan, which has come to be
known as the Sichelschnitt or sickle
cut. Earlier German plans had proposed a
right hook, swinging around against the
channel ports. The sickle cut was to be
a left hook, swinging up behind the
Allied armies waiting for their enemy to
pour across the Belgian border.
That left hook would be delivered by the
new concept of massed armor.
Walther Wenck, chief of operations of
the 1st Panzer Division, coined the
expression that best explains the
thinking behind German as opposed to
Allied armored tactics.
"Hit with your fist," Wenck said, "don't
feel with your fingers."
German armor would be the clenched fist,
not the splayed fingers of Allied
tactics, and it would race for
territory, not stop for a set piece
battle.
Von Manstein planned to exploit the weak
point that was the key to the whole
undoing of France.
The gap between the defense of the
Belgian border and the Maginot Line.
That gap was the forest of the Ardennes.
The point which German military
theorists called the Schwerpunkt, the
focal point or center of gravity.
For von Manstein, the Schwerpunkt was
the River Meuse between Sedan and
Dinant.
According to French planners, no attack
could be pressed through the thick
forest of the Ardennes, but according to
the Manstein plan, armor could move
through the forest and then, undetected,
burst into the rear of the Allied lines
as they faced the frontal attack being
pressed not just through Belgium, but
also the Netherlands, whose sovereignty
the Kaiser had respected 25 years
earlier.
>> Belgium and France were involved in the
First World War,
but the Netherlands was neutral.
And I suppose it will be all right.
Everybody was hoping
that things would not turn for the
worse.
>> Hitler gambled.
He ordered that all of the stockpiled
materials and munitions of war be
expended. The idea was that they would
be replenished from the conquered lands.
At the commencement of the invasion,
the Luftwaffe, for example, had enough
bombs for only 14 days of combat.
The Germans were, in every particular,
seriously outnumbered.
They had three army groups comprising
133 divisions. The Allies facing them
had 145
divisions, 3.7 million men to Germany's
2.7 million.
And on paper, at least, France on her
own was superior in tanks and aircraft.
Speaking in August 1941,
Hitler is reported to have said, "I
never use the word Blitzkrieg because it
is a very silly word."
But it is a word meaning literally
lightning war, which has become stuck,
limpet-like, to the idea of Germany's
mechanized offensives, the most
devastating of which began at 05:45
hours on the morning of May the 10th,
1940.
In less than 6 weeks, in as catastrophic
and humiliating a military defeat as can
be imagined, the battle would be over
and all the countries of continental
Europe that had neither allied with
Germany nor managed to preserve their
neutrality would be under Nazi control.
The plan that the German High Command,
the Oberkommando des Heeres or OKH, had
for the invasion of Western Europe
forecast the defeat of France and the
Low Countries and the isolation of Great
Britain.
But that was the extent of German
planning in the West. There was no plan
for the exploitation of conquered
territory. For that sort of vision, we
must turn our eyes, as Hitler did, to
the East, where German plans were very
different.
It was only to secure the German rear,
preparatory to initiating the plan for
the East, the Generalplan Ost, that
Hitler bothered with countries on his
western borders.
Once Western Europe was under his heel,
Hitler would turn to realize his great
vision of an empire in the East.
So, it was to secure the German rear
that Hitler launched the Manstein Plan.
A fearful demonstration of what war had
become.
General George Marshall, US President
Franklin D. Roosevelt's Chief of Staff,
saw, as early as 1940, that the
flag-waving days of warfare are gone.
Nikolai Voznesensky, Chief of the Soviet
State Planning Commission, warned of a
war of engines, a war that is won not on
the battlefield but in the factories.
It would not be flag-waving or glinting
sabers or scarlet tunics, but bombs and
shells and advancing armor that decided
the issue and most critically, not their
possession but their replenishment.
The strength of a German Panzer division
by March 1945
would amount to 54 tanks.
But in May 1940,
a Panzer division comprised 328
tanks and there was everything to play
for.
The German onslaught began with bombs as
the Luftwaffe attacked Allied airfields.
German airborne troops parachuted into
the Netherlands to seize vital bridges.
In Belgium,
the supposedly impregnable fortress of
Eben Emael, key to Liège, fell to
glider-borne troops who overcame its
defenses by the simple stratagem of
landing on its roof.
Units of von Bock's Army Group B crossed
the Dutch and Belgian borders luring the
Allies into taking the bait.
The Allied commander, French General
Gamelin, obliged, moving three French
armies and the entire British
Expeditionary Force, 40 divisions in
total, north to face the anticipated
invasion through Belgium.
But, the real threat was from Army Group
A in the center. Its seven panzer
divisions with 1,800 tanks smashed
through the Ardennes.
A part of German military philosophy was
Auftragstaktik, or mission tactics,
which encouraged and expected initiative
from commanders flexibly meeting local
conditions.
When the Blitzkrieg burst onto the
French and British defenses, it was the
initiative of generals like Heinz
Guderian and Erwin Rommel, whose growing
reputation would be later confirmed in
the desert battles of North Africa.
That drove their forces across country
as they defied the attempts of their
superiors to rein them in.
In the evening of what was day one of
the invasion, the British Prime Minister
Neville Chamberlain resigned from
office.
Cabinet Minister Leo Amery said of
Chamberlain that he loathed war so
passionately that he was determined to
wage as little of it as possible.
Chamberlain was replaced by Winston
Churchill, who did not loathe war,
having served in the First World War and
taken part in the last great British
cavalry charge at Omdurman in the Sudan
late in the 19th century. In May 1940,
Winston Churchill was 65 years old, only
five years younger than the man he
replaced.
>> The man to be pitied is Winston
Churchill. Among his colleagues, Mr.
Chamberlain, whose vacation of office
was accomplished in a manner worthy of
his great sincerity, remains as
Churchill's right hand.
>> Two days after Churchill took office on
May 12th, the leading German units
crossed into France, securing the north
bank of the Meuse.
On the 13th, the Dutch army was ordered
to fall back for a last stand on the
line Amsterdam-Rotterdam-Utrecht.
But the war was lost in the Netherlands,
and on the same day, Queen Wilhelmina
and her government evacuated to London.
>> On the 10th of May, Germany attacked
Denmark,
Norway,
Holland,
Belgium, and France, all on the same
day.
On the fifth day, the German Air Force
bombed Rotterdam.
A lot of damage was done. I'm not aware
how many people died, but I'm sure
people died.
And on that day, the Dutch High Command
surrendered.
So, now we're occupied. The first couple
of days in the occupation,
quite a few Jewish families committed
suicide.
How many? I don't know, but the rumor
came through Amsterdam.
This family, that family.
>> The relentless German assault was now
pressing the allies all along the front.
The Netherlands was out of the war. Army
Group Army Groups A and B was moving
against the French Ninth Army, which
disintegrated.
The German 12th and 16th Armies, having
crossed the Meuse, were threatening the
rear of the Allied position.
In Paris, they tried an appeal to the
almighty.
>> In their hour of anxiety, the French
people hear the summons to prayer. At
Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, a solemn
service of intercession is held.
The Prime Minister, Monsieur Reynaud,
attends and Monsieur Daladier with the
American Ambassador.
>> On the day that the Netherlands
surrendered, the French Prime Minister
had telephoned his British counterpart.
"We have been defeated." Paul Reynaud
said, "We are beaten. We have lost the
battle."
Churchill could only answer,
"Surely it can't have happened so soon."
But it had.
In his telephone call to Churchill,
Reynaud was reacting to news from the
battlefield that if any one action can
be said to have been responsible, sealed
the fate of France. The battlefield at
Sedan.
On September the 1st, 1870, a Prussian
force had destroyed the French army at
Sedan, forcing the abdication of the
emperor and advancing the cause of
German unification under Prussian
stewardship.
This historical resonance added
something to the significance of a
battle now being fought over the same
ground.
On the 16th of May, the allies began to
withdraw from Belgium. On the 17th, the
fighting at Sedan ended with a German
victory.
In 7 days, the Germans had advanced 320
km, crossed the Meuse, and broken into
the undefended Allied rear. On the 7th
day of the invasion, Brussels, the
Belgian capital, fell.
German tanks were reported to be
refueling at local petrol stations.
German troops were seen milking cows
abandoned in the fields.
In close support of the tanks and the
following infantry were the artillery
and the Luftwaffe.
The German Air Force had been designed
to support action on the ground. Its
later shortcomings can be traced to this
priority, but in the invasion of France,
they were not shortcomings.
German fighters dominated the skies, and
both military and civilians feared
nothing so much as the shrieking
approach of the Junkers 87, the Stuka,
short for Sturzkampfflugzeug,
dive bomber, equipped with a
mischievously terrifying device that the
Germans called the Jericho Trumpet.
The Jericho Trumpet, a propeller-driven
siren tube that made the approaching
aircraft with its banshee howl as
menacing as some fantastical beast.
>> We got off at Calais and I thought,
"What's going on here?" And the
restaurant on the quayside, the windows
are all broken. And I was rather
puzzled, you know, still didn't still
didn't click.
All of a sudden the planes came over.
And they came screaming down.
The screaming bomber's coming down, and
these Stukas driving made a horrible
screaming noise.
We dashed amongst the sand dunes,
clawed at the earth, trying to get
underground.
You just Fear is just overpowering.
And I knew then that was war.
>> On May the 19th, Gamelin was replaced as
Allied commander by General Weygand, but
it was too late.
The 7th Panzer Division under Rommel had
reached Cambrai on the 18th, and on the
20th, German armor reached the English
Channel and the mouth of the River
Somme, where so much blood had been
spilled in the First World War.
This thrust effectively split the Allied
armies in two.
The Allies attempted a counter-attack,
but where the Germans massed their 2,700
tanks,
the Allies still thought of the tank as
an infantry support weapon and had their
3,000 machines widely dispersed along
the entire front.
Britain and French counter-offensives
were also poorly coordinated and the
disruption to the German advance was
momentary.
Following the blunted Allied
counter-attack, the Germans turned
north,
pressing for the prize that had evaded
the Kaiser's troops 25 years earlier,
the Channel ports.
Boulogne fell on the 25th and Calais,
bitterly defended by the British on the
27th. Before then, an order which has
puzzled many ever since changed the
character of the battle.
On May the 24th, Army Groups A and B
linked up and Group von Kleist stopped
less than 25 km from Dunkirk, where it
was opposed by a single low-grade French
division and a weak British infantry
force. And then, in one of the war's
regular and somewhat inexplicable
turning points, it was ordered to halt.
The day following the halt order, Hitler
visited Army Group A's headquarters and
he confirmed von Rundstedt's decision.
We question the decision because with
hindsight, we can see how feeble French
resistance was beyond this point and how
cheaply French capitulation was sold.
For Hitler and his generals, the bulk of
France's armed forces was yet to be
conquered and after two hard weeks of
fighting, many of Germany's armored
units had been reduced to 30% of their
tank strength.
Surely a pause to reform and re-equip
would be prudent.
They could not have known that prudence
was not required.
On May the 25th, the day after Hitler's
visit to the front, Lord Gort,
commanding the British Expeditionary
Force, was advised by the Belgians,
commanded by King Leopold, that their
situation was desperate.
Gort decided that his duty lay in saving
his army to fight another day, rather
than seeing it sacrificed for a lost
cause.
He began to withdraw his forces on
Dunkirk, and the following day, May the
26th, almost 28,000 men not central to
the BEF's fighting capacity were
evacuated.
>> The road from Boulogne was just full of
moving bodies. That's all That's all I
could call them.
Because they didn't look like people.
They were men, women, and children with
bags,
dragging little trucks.
The children weren't talking or playing.
All with vacant vacant expressions, just
looking straight ahead.
Going nowhere.
>> Reichsmarschall Hermann Göring,
commanding the German Air Force,
rejoiced that the kill of the troops
trapped at Dunkirk would be left to his
Luftwaffe.
But the Luftwaffe could not do the job.
The bombers could not find their targets
at night, and the fighters could not
operate effectively.
It took one more miracle for the troops
at Dunkirk to be saved. The notorious
English Channel was, for the duration of
the operation, a calm sea.
On the 26th of May, the halt order was
rescinded, but it was too late. An
armada had been organized, an effective
defense perimeter had been established,
and 330,000
Allied troops were assembled at Dunkirk
to be evacuated.
There were 222 Royal Navy and
approximately 860 civilian vessels at
Dunkirk.
Instead of the 45,000 hoped for, the
fleet took off 338,000
Allied troops.
>> On the way down the harbor, they were
shelling us and I dropped into the
gutter a couple of times.
The harbor was full of sunken ships and
at the quayside, I could see somebody
running in front of me. I see him
running and he was running and I
thought, "Ooh, that ship's got smoke
coming out of the funnel." So, I ran
like mad as well and we're just pulling
away from the quayside and I managed to
get the boat.
>> 40% of those evacuated from Dunkirk,
170,000
men, were French troops. They were
returned to their own shores in
southwestern France to carry on the
fight.
Following France's capitulation, they
were out of the war.
Dunkirk had saved the bulk of the
British Expeditionary Force,
but that army had been effectively
disarmed. It left behind 64,000 vehicles
and 2,500 guns. Those evacuated were, to
all intents and purposes, beaten,
but they were not defeated and they were
not pursued.
>> When I first joined up
uh my training was pretty much the same
as the 1914-18 war.
Uh the Enfield rifle with a big 18-in
long bayonet.
And
jumping in and out of trenches, charging
at bundles of twigs or sacks of straw
and stabbing them.
And of course it wasn't until uh
Dunkirk uh the time of Dunkirk where we
learned that there's another way of
fighting which was the blitzkrieg.
And that's been shown to us by the
Germans.
>> The evacuation continued until June the
4th when the Germans entered Dunkirk.
The following day they resumed their
offensive pushing south into France. By
the 9th the French had been driven from
the Somme. The outcome was hardly in
doubt and on the 10th sensing victory
Mussolini declared war on Britain and
France and the French government removed
itself from Paris.
Mussolini's caution is understandable.
His army was both smaller and less well
equipped than it had been in 1915.
On the 11th of June Paris was declared
an open city in the hope that this would
save it from bombing and destruction. On
June the 14th General Bogislav von
Studnitz led the 87th Infantry Division
of the Wehrmacht through the almost
deserted streets of the French capital.
The next day, June the 15th, 400,000
Frenchmen of the surrounded 3rd, 5th,
and 8th armies surrendered en masse.
Whilst on the other side of Europe in an
opportunistic move the Soviet Union
expanded its empire by liquidating
Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia as
independent nations.
On June the 17th, the 86-year-old
Marshall Pétain, the hero of Verdun in
the First World War, whose recall to
Paris from his post as ambassador to
Spain had been greeted by cheering
crowds, announced that he had taken over
as head of state and was seeking an
armistice.
The panic in his country that this
announcement must have been calculated
to quell is best illustrated by the 8
million French people who had abandoned
their homes since the invasion began.
It was seeing some of these civilians on
the road being strafed by a German
fighter aircraft that led a British
airman to say, "So they are shits after
all."
The Dutch and Belgian governments,
though the Belgian king remained in his
country, went into exile and many urged
the French to do the same.
Perhaps relocating to French colonies in
North Africa and continuing the fight
from there.
But the government of Marshall Pétain
chose instead to surrender.
An editorial in O Comércio do Porto, a
newspaper in the Portugal of dictator
António Salazar, declared that the war
is a sorry advertisement for democracy.
As the military disaster was unfolding,
there was talk in England of relocating
the British royal family to Canada. A
faction in the British cabinet led by
Lord Halifax, the foreign secretary, who
had been favored by both Chamberlain and
the king to become Prime Minister
proposed putting out peace feelers using
Mussolini as an intermediary.
But Halifax had declined the top job and
the man who had been handed what many
thought was a poisoned chalice was
having none of it. Winston Churchill
began at once to mobilize the weapon
that he would use to such great effect
throughout the war.
The English language.
>> That heartening broadcast of Mr. Winston
Churchill's was a tonic to all who heard
it.
>> We tried again and again to prevent this
war.
And for the sake of peace we put up with
a lot of things happening
which ought not to have happened.
But now we are at war.
And we are going to make war.
And pursue the aim of making war
until the other side have had enough of
it.
>> If Churchill sounds different to the
voice familiar from the stirring
speeches he delivered as Prime Minister,
it is because the Prime Minister did not
have time to travel to Broadcasting
House and record for the nation the
speeches he made in the House of Commons
which was not wired for sound.
So an actor named Norman Shelley,
the voice of Larry the Lamb on the BBC's
Children's Hour, was the voice of
Winston Churchill for several radio
broadcasts.
On the 18th of June, Marshall Petain
placed Reynaud as Prime Minister. It was
the day that Churchill made the speech
in the Commons in which he swore that if
the British Empire and its Commonwealth
last a thousand years, men will say this
was their finest hour.
It was not France's finest hour.
That same day Charles de Gaulle
broadcast from London.
He told the French people, "This war has
not been settled by the Battle of
France. This is a world war.
We believe that the honor of the French
depends on continuing the war at the
side of our allies."
>> And what what I fancy is going to embark
on a big ship.
We left We left France in June 1940
when France collapsed.
Oh, I went to England.
And then I learned that de Gaulle
was staying on board with the other
British.
We were told to find out where was de
Gaulle which cuz he was a general.
Nobody knew who he was.
After a few days of inquiry,
we uh
we decided to find de Gaulle.
I found de Gaulle on the 13th of July
1940.
>> On the day that de Gaulle made his
appeal, Churchill said in his finest
hour speech, "The Battle of France is
over. I expect that the Battle of
Britain is about to begin."
In one of history's strange ironies,
these speeches were made on the day that
marked the 125th anniversary of the
Battle of Waterloo when Britain,
with her German allies, had defeated the
French under Napoleon.
On June the 17th, Britain had suffered
its worst ever maritime disaster, about
three times worse than the Titanic.
The Cunarder Lancastria, carrying
between 6 and 9,000 evacuees, troops,
and civilians who had been left in
France after the Dunkirk operation, had
been sunk by German aircraft. Only 2,500
were saved.
Churchill imposed a news blackout on the
event. He felt that the British people
were receiving quite enough bad news.
On June the 20th, Lyon fell and a
general ceasefire was declared in
France. More than 1 and 1/2 million
French troops became German prisoners.
When Charles de Gaulle called for
continued resistance, General Weygand,
his commander-in-chief, said,
"Nonsense." He said, "In 3 weeks,
England will have her neck wrung like a
chicken."
"Some chicken," Churchill was later
famously to remark.
"Some neck."
France's formal surrender was signed on
June the 22nd. France, if not quite all
of the French, was out of the war. The
Kaiser, who had abdicated at the very
end of the First World War, telegrammed
Hitler from his exile in the
Netherlands. "My Führer," he wrote, "I
congratulate you and hope that under
your marvelous leadership, the German
monarchy will be restored completely."
Hitler turned to his valet.
"What an idiot," he said.
The Blitzkrieg was a military disaster,
but not a military defeat.
The French armed forces were still in
the field when the government
capitulated and after the armistice,
1,700 of France's frontline aircraft
were found distributed amongst airfields
in the unoccupied zone. They had never
flown against the Germans.
The fall of France was the result not of
her defeat, but of her surrender.
The Vichy regime that became the
government of France, Vichy is the small
spa town in which it was located, stands
shoulder to shoulder with the most
controversial topics of the Second World
War.
Was Marshal Philippe Pétain the shield
of France who had saved his country from
the humiliation of total defeat, or was
he happy to reach an early accommodation
with was he sympathetic with Hitler's
ideology?
In 1934,
as the dictators were starting to rise,
the French newspaper Le Petit Journal
ran a poll.
France endured 42 weak governments
between the wars, and the poll asked,
"Who should take over as dictator?"
Philippe Petain was the popular pick
with 200,000 votes. Second was Pierre
Laval, who would become Vichy's prime
minister.
He received 31,000.
When Petain formed his government, he
effectively abolished the Republic.
He got rid of the motto that had served
since the revolution,
liberty, equality, brotherhood, and
replaced it with travail, famille,
patrie, work, family, fatherland. France
would now, Petain said, be a new
society,
rejecting the false idea of the equality
of men.
The armistice that Petain agreed to
accepted German occupation of 3/5 of
France, the industrial heartland, the
border region with Germany, and the
whole of the Atlantic and Channel
coastline.
The Vichy government nominally ruled
over the country, but in reality
exercised complete sovereignty only over
the so-called zone libre, the free zone.
Petain also agreed to pay the full costs
of the occupation, which were grossly
overstated by the Germans.
France overall is estimated to have
contributed 42% of the Reich's external
aid through the war.
Supply from French farms and factories,
supply of French labor to German
factories, acquisition of French
military hardware, and the continued
detention in Germany of 1.5 million
French prisoners of war were all part of
a very one-sided armistice.
France was allowed to keep her overseas
empire and her navy. And it was the
French fleet that caused the greatest
immediate concern to the British
government. It sought reassurance that
the fleet would not be allowed to fall
into Axis hands. Receiving no such
assurance, the Royal Navy blockaded the
fleet at its North African bases in Mers
el-Kébir and Oran.
On July the 3rd, Admiral James
Somerville communicated his terms to the
French Admiral Marcel Bruno Gensoul.
It is impossible for us, your comrades
up to now, to allow your fine ships to
fall into the power of the German enemy,
he wrote.
His Majesty's government have instructed
me to demand that the French fleet shall
act in accordance with one of the
following alternatives.
And he listed joining him, scuttling the
fleet, or sailing away with reduced
crews to some French port in the West
Indies where they can be demilitarized
to our satisfaction, or perhaps be
entrusted to the United States.
Failing the above, I have orders from
His Majesty's government to use whatever
force may be necessary to prevent your
ships from falling into German hands.
But Admiral Gensoul would not comply.
Somerville opened fire.
>> The first engagement between British and
French forces since Waterloo
resulted in the deaths of 1,297
French servicemen,
the sinking of a battleship, damage to
five other ships, and to the
Anglo-French relationship.
Britain was now alone, but at least
thanks to Dunkirk, she still had some
sort of an army. Importantly, in terms
of recognizing that the war was far from
over, it should be remembered that the
British Expeditionary Force represented
a small proportion of the forces
available to Britain from within a
reasonably unified empire, an empire
that was mobilizing to her aid as it had
done a generation earlier. Those in the
Dominions would again demonstrate their
readiness to pay the price of empire.
>> It wasn't till uh May and June 1940
where you were learned that Britain
really had her back to the wall and
looked like being invaded by the Nazis.
So, there was a an outpouring of
patriotic fervors up and down Australia,
and fellas by the thousand, literally by
the thousand, are rushing to join up so
as to go and help Britain.
>> But, the price of empire is not evenly
shared. Amongst French troops left to
fall into German hands were thousands
from France's African possessions.
About 10,000 were killed in the fighting
and among those taken prisoner it is
estimated that as many as 3,000 were
shot out of hand in a racially motivated
crime.
Following the evacuation from Dunkirk
and the fall of France, orders were
given in Britain that the church bells,
which peeled every Sunday, were not to
be rung again except to signal an
invasion.
And an invasion of the British Isles by
a rampant Germany was everyone's
expectation. After all, considered
numerically, the troops restored to
British soil meant that if the Wehrmacht
invaded, they would face weaker
opposition than they had brushed aside
in Belgium and the Netherlands.
Instead of an invasion in mid-July, the
Luftwaffe dropped leaflets over England.
They were titled A Last Appeal to
Reason.
On July the 19th, Hitler said, "I feel
it is my duty before my own conscience
to appeal once more to reason and common
sense in Great Britain." The controversy
over whether the peace overtures to
Britain were sincere, whether peace
would have been possible, persists. To
the moment of his death, Adolf Hitler
would talk about the war that was forced
on me and describe Winston Churchill as
a warmonger.
>> Hello.
Good luck to you all.
Keep it up.
It's going well. You're all playing a
part.
>> When Churchill became Prime Minister,
his country was already at war and the
evidence of the cruel and destructive
ambitions of Hitler was overwhelming.
Peace may have been possible, but it
strains credibility to suppose that it
could have been a lasting peace or a
peace in which the United Kingdom would
have been better treated than France,
obliged to allow occupation, stripped of
her military strength, and forced to pay
a sum equivalent to 50 times the actual
cost of the occupation.
Churchill wanted no part of it. He told
the British people in the first of his
landmark speeches, "We shall go on to
the end." He told them, "We shall fight
on the sea and oceans." He said, "We
shall defend our island, whatever the
cost may be." He promised, "We shall
never surrender."
And he meant it.
Which is why at this exact time on July
the 18th, the day before Hitler's
conciliatory statement, Churchill closed
the Burma Road.
Although the conflicts of East and West
were yet to merge into one great affair,
this was already a world war.
Burma was part of the British Empire. It
had been made so by Churchill's father,
Lord Randolph Churchill. And the road,
which was never more than a precarious
single track along which trucks lumbered
slowly, carried up to 30,000 tons of
supplies a day to support China's fight
against Japan.
On the 18th of July, 1940,
Churchill, the great enemy of
appeasement, yielded to Japanese
pressure and closed the Burma Road.
He later defended his action by saying
that leaving the road open would have
meant something dangerous might have
happened.
Something dangerous would have been
Japan taking matters into its own hands,
moving against Burma, and forcing
Britain into a war on two fronts.
But appeasing Japan did not prevent
danger.
On the The that Churchill closed the
Burma Road, the military party in Japan
triumphed and General Hideki Tojo, who
would later achieve notoriety as wartime
Prime Minister, became Minister for war.
A few days later, Japan announced its
aim of creating a greater East Asia
Co-Prosperity Sphere.
In September 1940, Japan occupied
Indochina and signed a Tripartite Pact
with Rome and Berlin.
The threat to Britain's empire in the
East was becoming palpably real. The
price of empire was going up.
Hitler was a great admirer of the
British empire.
In Mein Kampf, he made clear his
admiration for the British empire and
Lives of a Bengal Lancer was his
favorite film.
"What India was for England," Adolf
Hitler would say before launching the
invasion of the Soviet Union.
"The territories of Russia will be for
us."
He believed that the two empires could
coexist and on August the 14th, the day
after the Battle of Britain began, told
the 12 generals that he had raised to
field marshal that Germany would not
benefit from defeating Great Britain.
"The beneficiaries of that," Hitler
said, "would be Japan in Asia, Russia in
India, Italy in the Mediterranean, and
the United States in world trade. That,"
Hitler said, "is why peace is possible
with Britain."
But it was not.
In the next episode of The Price of
Empire, the only opposition to Hitler
and the Third Reich is the United
Kingdom and her empire.
Germany begins assembling a fleet for
the cross-channel invasion and launches
an air war.
The Battle of Britain
to gain aerial superiority and to weaken
civilian morale.
It was the time when the darkest hour
became the finest hour.